What I want to talk about is, as background,
ما أريد التحدث عنه, كخلفية,
is the idea that cars are art.
هو فكرة أن السيارات فن.
This is actually quite meaningful to me,
و هو شيء يعني لي الكثير,
because car designers tend to be a little bit low on the totem pole --
لأن مصممي السيارات عادة ما يكونون منخفضين على الصعيد الإنتمائي,
we don't do coffee table books with just one lamp inside of it --
نحن لا نصنع طاولات قهوة للكتب تحتوي على مجرد ضوء واحد,
and cars are thought so much as a product
و السيارات يتم فهمها على أنها منتجات
that it's a little bit difficult to get into the aesthetic side
حتى أنه أصبح من الصعب الدخول في الجانب الجمالي
under the same sort of terminology that one would discuss art.
تحت نفس المسمى الذي سيناقشه المرء كفن.
And so cars, as art, brings it into an emotional plane -- if you accept that --
و كذلك هي السيارات, كفن, تحضره إلى مجال عاطفي --إن شئت--
that you have to deal with on the same level you would with art with a capital A.
و الذي عليك التعامل معه بنفس المستوى الذي كنت ستتعامل فيه مع الفن.
Now at this point you're going to see a picture of Michelangelo.
الآن, ستشاهد صورة لمايكل آنجلو.
This is completely different than automobiles.
ما تراه هو مختلف كلياً عن السيارات.
Automobiles are self-moving things, right? Elevators are automobiles.
الآلات هي أشياء تتحرك لوحدها, أليس كذلك؟ المصاعد هي آلات
And they're not very emotional; they solve a purpose;
و هي ليست عاطفية بدرجة كبيرة, هي تؤدي وظيفة,
and certainly automobiles have been around for 100 years
و الآلات موجودة منذ 100 سنة
and have made our lives functionally a lot better in many ways;
و قد استطاعت أن تحسن حياتنا بطرق عديدة,
they've also been a real pain in the ass,
و لكنها في الجانب الآخر سببت لنا الكثير من المتاعب.
because automobiles are really the thing we have to solve.
لأن السيارات, حقيقة, هو الشيء الذي يجب علينا أن نجد له حلاً.
We have to solve the pollution, we have to solve the congestion --
علينا أن نحل مشكلة التلوث, و علينا أن نحل مشكلة الإزدحام.
but that's not what interests me in this speech.
و لكن ليس هذا ما يهمني في هذا الحديث.
What interests me in this speech is cars. Automobiles may be what you use,
ما يهمني في هذا الحديث هي السيارات. الآلات هي ربما الأشياء التي نستخدمها,
but cars are what we are, in many ways.
و لكن السيارات هي من نحن, بعدة طرق.
And as long as we can solve the problems of automobiles,
طالما كنا قادرين على حل مشكلات الآلات,
and I believe we can, with fuel cells or hydrogen, like BMW is really hip on,
و أنا أؤمن أنه بإمكاننا فعل ذلك,
and lots of other things, then I think we can look past that
و الكثير من الأشياء الأخرى, و أؤمن أيضاً, أننا نستطيع أن نتجاوز ذلك إلى ما هو أبعد منه.
and try and understand why this hook is in many of us --
و نحاول أن نفهم لماذا هذا الكلاب هو في داخل الكثيرين منا --
of this car-y-ness -- and what that means, what we can learn from it.
من هذا التعلق الشديد بالسيارات, و ما يعنيه هذا الأمر, و ما الذي نستطيع أن نتعلمه منه
That's what I want to get to. Cars are not a suit of clothes;
و هذا ما أريد أن أصل إليه. السيارات ليست عبارة عن ملابس,
cars are an avatar. Cars are an expansion of yourself:
السيارات هي أفاتار, السيارات هي انعكاس لنفسك,
they take your thoughts, your ideas, your emotions, and they multiply it --
يستوحذون على أفكارك, و أحاسيسك, و من ثم يستدخمونها --
your anger, whatever. It's an avatar.
أو حتى غضبك, أياً كان. إنه أفاتار
It's a super-waldo that you happen to be inside of, and if you feel sexy,
إنها سوبر والدو أصبحت بداخلها بطريقة ما, و إن كنت تشعر بأنك مثير,
the car is sexy. And if you're full of road rage,
فإن السيارة مثيرة. و إن كنت مليئاً بغضب الطريق,
you've got a "Chevy: Like a Rock," right?
فسيكون لديك "شيفي: كالنجم, " أليس كذلك؟
Cars are a sculpture -- did you know this?
السيارات هي تمثال -- هل كنت تعلم هذا؟
That every car you see out there is sculpted by hand.
أن كل سيارة تراها هي منحوتة باليد
Many people think, "Well, it's computers,
العديد من الناس يظنون, "حسناً إنها حواسيب,
and it's done by machines and stuff like that."
و هي تُصنع بالآلات و ما شابه."
Well, they reproduce it, but the originals are all done by hand.
حسناً, هم يصنعونها, و لكن الأصليات كلها يتم إنتاجها عن طريق اليد.
It's done by men and women who believe a lot in their craft.
يتم تصنيعها من قبل رجال و نساء يؤمنون كثيراً بصناعتهم.
And they put that same kind of tension into the sculpting of a car
و هم يضعون نفس مقدار هذا الجهد في نحت سيارة
that you do in a great sculpture that you would go and look at in a museum.
نوع من النحت الذي تقوم به و الذي سيجعلك تذهب إلى المتحف لمشاهدته.
That tension between the need to express, the need to discover,
ذاك التوتر بين الحاجة للتعبير, و الحاجة للإكتشاف,
then you put something new into it,
و بعدها تضع شيئاً جديداً فيه
and at the same time you have bounds of craftsmanship.
و في نفس الوقت لديك العديد من العمالة الماهرة.
Rules that say, this is how you handle surfaces;
القوانين التي تقول, بأنه هكذا يتم التعامل مع الأسطح,
this is what control is all about; this is how you show you're a master of your craft.
و هذا هو التحكم, و هكذا تُظهر للناس أنك أستاذ في حرفتك.
And that tension, that discovery, that push for something new --
و هذا التوتر, هذا الإكتشاف, هذا الدفع لشيء جديد --
and at the same time, that sense of obligation
و في نفس الوقت, هذا الإحساس بالالتزام
to the regards of craftsmanship --
تجاه ما يتعلق بالبراعة في الحرفة --
that's as strong in cars as it is in anything.
و هذا موجود بقوة في السيارات كما في أي شيء آخر.
We work in clay, which hasn't changed much
نحن نعمل بالطين, و الذي لم يتغير كثيراً
since Michelangelo started screwing around with it,
منذ أن بدأ مايكل آنجلو بالعبث به,
and there's a very interesting analogy to that too.
و هنالك قياس مثير للإهتمام تجاه ذلك أيضاً.
Real quickly -- Michelangelo once said he's there to "discover the figure within," OK?
بسرعة -- مايكل آنجلو قال مرة أنه هناك لـ "إكتشاف الصورة الضمنية"
There we go, the automobile.
و ها نحن ذا, الآلة.
That was 100 years right there -- did you catch that?
كان هذا 100 سنة, هل فهمتم ذلك؟
Between that one there, and that one there, it changed a lot didn't it?
تغير الكثير بين الإثنين, أليس كذلك؟
OK, it's not marketing; there's a very interesting car concept here,
حسناً, إنه ليس تسويق, هنالك مفهوم للسيارات مثير للإهتمام هنا,
but the marketing part is not what I want to talk about here.
و لكن موضوع التسويق ليس هو الشيء الذي أود التحدث عنه في هذا المقام.
I want to talk about this.
أريد أن أتحدث عن هذا.
Why it means you have to wash a car, what is it, that sensuality
ما الذي يعنيه أنه عليك أن تغسل سيارة, ما هي, تلك الشهوانية
you have to touch about it? That's the sculpture that goes into it. That sensuality.
التي عليك أن تلمس فيها؟ هذا هو النحت الذي يدخل فيها. تلك الشهوانية.
And it's done by men and women working just like this, making cars.
و يتم عملها عن طريق رجال و نساء, يعملون هكذا, يصنعون سيارات.
Now this little quote about sculpture from Henry Moore,
و الآن هذه المقولة القصيرة عن السيارات لهنري مور,
I believe that that "pressure within" that Moore's talking about --
أنا أؤمن بأن ذلك "الضغط الذاتي" الذي يتحدث عنه مور --
at least when it comes to cars --
على الأقل عندما يتعلق الأمر بالسيارات
comes right back to this idea of the mean.
يعود مباشرة لفكرة هذا المعنى.
It's that will to live, that need to survive, to express itself,
أنه الرغبة في العيش, الرغبة للنجاة, للتعبير عن الذات,
that comes in a car, and takes over people like me.
و الذي يأتي مع السيارة, و يستحوذ على أشخاص مثلي.
And we tell other people, "Do this, do this, do this," until this thing comes alive.
و نحن نقول للناس "افعل هذا, افعل هذا, افعل هذا" حتى يصبح هذا الشيء على قيد الحياة.
We are completely infected. And beauty can be the result
نحن مصابون بالكامل. و الجمال يمكن أن يكون هو النتيجة
of this infectiousness; it's quite wonderful.
لهذا الإصابة, إنه لشيء رائع حقاً.
This sculpture is, of course, at the heart of all of it,
هذا النحت, بالطبع, هو في صميم كل هذه الأشياء,
and it's really what puts the craftsmanship into our cars.
و هو الشيء الحقيقي الذي يضع هذه البراعة في سياراتنا.
And it's not a whole lot different, really, when they're working like this,
و هو ليس بذلك الفرق الكبير, حقاً, عندما يعملون هكذا,
or when somebody works like this.
أو حتى هكذا.
It's that same kind of commitment, that same kind of beauty.
إنه نفس نوع الإرتباط, و نفس نوع الجمال.
Now, now I get to the point. I want to talk about cars as art.
الآن, الآن أصل إلى فكرتي. أريد أن أتحدث عن السيارات كفن.
Art, in the Platonic sense, is truth; it's beauty, and love.
الفن, في الحس الأفلاطوني, هو الحقيقة, هو الجمال, و الحب.
Now this is really where designers in car business diverge from the engineers.
هذه هي حتماً, النقطة التي يبتعد فيها الفنانون عن المهندسون.
We don't really have a problem talking about love.
ليست لدينا أي مشكلة البتة في أن نتحدث عن الحب.
We don't have a problem talking about truth or beauty in that sense.
ليست لدينا أي مشكلة في أن نتحدث عن الحقيقة أو الجمال في نفس السياق.
That's what we're searching for --
بل هذا هو ما نحن نبحث عنه --
when we're working our craft, we are really trying to find that truth out there.
عندما نكون نعمل على حرفتنا, نحاول جاهدين في أن نجد الحقيقة فيه.
We're not trying to find vanity and beauty.
نحن لا نحاول أن نجد الغرور و الجمال.
We're trying to find the beauty in the truth.
نحل نحاول أن نجد الجمال في الحقيقة.
However, engineers tend to look at things a little bit more Newtonian,
و لكن, المهندسون دائماً ما ينظرون للأشياء بطريقة أكثر "نيوتنية",
instead of this quantum approach.
بدلاً من هذا النهج الكمي.
We're dealing with irrationalisms,
نحن نتعامل مع الغير منطقيات,
and we're dealing with paradoxes that we admit exist,
و نحن نتعامل مع مفارقات نؤمن نحن بوجودها,
and the engineers tend to look things a little bit more like
و المهندسون, في المقابل, عادةً ما ينظرون للأشياء بطريقة هي أقرب إلى
two and two is four, and if you get 4.0 it's better, and 4.000 is even better.
إثنان و إثنان أربعة, و إن حصلت على 4.0 فهذا أفضل, و 4.0000 فهذا أفضل بكثير.
And that sometimes leads to bit of a divergence
و هذه المفارقة عادةً ما تؤدي إلى اختلاف
in why we're doing what we're doing.
في سبب فعلنا لما نفعله.
We've pretty much accepted the fact, though,
و لكننا قبلنا إلى حد بعيد هذه الحقيقة,
that we are the women in the organization at BMW --
أننا نحن من هم النساء في بي أم دبليو --
BMW is a very manly type business, -- men, men, men; it's engineers.
بي أم دبليو هو نوع رجولي جدا من العمل, -- رجال, رجال, رجال, إنها مهندسون.
And we're kind of the female side to that. That's OK,
و نحن الجانب النسائي من المعادلة. و هذا مقبول,
that's cool. You go off and be manly. We're going to be a little bit more female.
و هذا جيد, إذهب أنت و كن رجولياً, و نحن سنكون نسائيين بعض الشيء.
Because what we're interested in is finding form that's more than just a function.
لأن الذي يهمنا هو أن نجد شكلاً يكون أكثر من مجرد وظيفة.
We're interested in finding beauty that's more than just an aesthetic;
نحن مهتمون في إيجاد نوع من الجمال, يكون أكثر من مجرد جمالية
it's really a truth.
أن يكون الحقيقة بحق.
And I think this idea of soul, as being at the heart of great cars,
و أنا أتخيل فكرة الروح هذه, كحجر الزاوية للسيارات العظيمة,
is very applicable. You all know it. You know a car when you've seen it,
و هي قابلة للتطبيق إلى حد بعيد. كلكم تعرفون هذا. عندما تعرف سيارة ما عندما تراها,
with soul. You know how strong this is.
بروح. و تدرك كم هو قوي هذا الشعور .
Well, this experience of love, and the experience of design, to me,
في الواقع, هذه التجربة للحب, و تجربة التصميم, هي بالنسبة لي
are interchangeable. And now I'm coming to my story.
أشياء قابلة للتبادل. و أنا الآن سآتي إلى قصتي.
I discovered something about love and design through a project called Deep Blue.
لقد اكتشفت شيئاً عن الحب و التصميم بفضل مشروع كان اسمه ديب بلو.
And first of all, you have to go with me for a second, and say,
و أولاً و قبل كل شيء, يجب أن تتخيل معي قليلاً و تقول,
you know, you could take the word "love" out of a lot of things in our society,
يمكنك أن تنتزع كلمة حب من الكثير من الأشياء في مجتمعنا,
put the word "design" in, and it still works,
و أن تضع بدلاً منها كلمة تصميم, و لا زلت ستحصل على نفس المعنى,
like this quote here, you know. It kind of works, you know?
تماماً كهذه المقولة الشهيرة هنا, إنها لا زالت تحمل نفس المعنى, أتعلمون؟
You can understand that. It works in truisms.
يمكنك أن تفهم ذلك. تعمل ببديهية.
"All is fair in design and war."
"كل شيء عادل في التصميم و الحرب."
Certainly we live in a competitive society.
نحن بالتأكيد نعيش في مجتمع تنافسي.
I think this one here, there's a pop song
أعتقد أن هذه هنا, هنالك أغنية بوب
that really describes Philippe Starck for me, you know, this is like
و التي تصف حقاً فيليب ستارك لي, أتعلمون, إنها كـ
you know, this is like puppy love, you know, this is cool right?
أتعلمون, إنها كحب الجرو, أتعلمون, هذا جيد, أليس كذلك؟
Toothbrush, cool.
فرشاة أسنان, جيد.
It really only gets serious when you look at something like this. OK?
إنها فقط تصبح مثيرة للإهتمام بحق عندما تنظر لشيء كهذ. حسناً؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
This is one substitution that I believe
هذا بديل أؤمن أن
all of us, in design management, are guilty of.
جميعنا, في إدارة التصميم, متورطون فيه.
And this idea that there is more to love,
و فكرة أن هناك المزيد في الحب,
more to design, when it gets down to your neighbor, your other,
المزيد في التصميم, عندما يتعلق الأمر بالحي الذي تسكن فيه, بشخصك الآخر,
it can be physical like this, and maybe in the future it will be.
يمكن أن تصبح فيزيائياً كهذا, و ربما في المستقبل ستصبح حقاً كذلك.
But right now it's in dealing with our own people,
و لكن في الوقت الراهن, إنها تتعامل مع أناساً خاصتنا,
our own teams who are doing the creating. So, to my story.
فرقنا نحن هي من تصنع القصة. إذاً, إلى قصتي.
The idea of people-work is what we work with here,
فكرة الناس-العمل هي التي نتعامل معها هنا,
and I have to make a bond with my designers when we're creating BMWs.
و يجب علي أن أصنع حلقة وصل بين المصممين عندما نصنع سيارات بي أم دبليو.
We have to have a shared intimacy, a shared vision --
يجب أن يكون لدينا ألفة مشتركة, رؤية مشتركة
that means we have to work as one family;
و هذا يعني أنه يجب علينا أن نعمل كعائلة واحدة,
we have to understand ourselves that way.
يجب علينا أن نفهم بعضنا بهذه الطريقة.
There's good times; there's interesting times;
هنالك أوقات جيدة, أوقات مثيرة للأهتمام,
and there's some stress times too.
و هنالك أوقات عصيبة كذلك.
You want to do cars, you've got to go outside.
إن أردت أن تصنع السيارات, عليك أن تذهب إلى الخارج.
You've got to do cars in the rain; you've got to do cars in the snow.
يجب عليك أن تصنع السيارات في المطر, يجب عليك أن تصنع السيارات في الثلج.
That's, by the way, is a presentation we made to our board of directors.
و هذه, بالمناسبة, كانت مسرحية قدمناها لمجلس إداراتنا.
We haul their butts out in the snow, too. You want to know cars outside?
نحن نقوم بتعذيبهم في الخارج. أتريد أن تعرف السيارة و هي في الخارج؟
Well, you've got to stand outside to do this.
حسناً, يجب عليك أن تقف في الخارج لكي تفعل ذلك.
And because these are artists, they have very artistic temperaments.
و لأن هؤلاء هم فنانون, لديهم مزاجات فنية للغاية.
All right? Now one thing about art is, art is discovery,
أفهمتم؟ هنالك شيء واحد عن الفن, ألا و هو الإكتشاف,
and art is discovering yourself through your art. Right?
و الفن هو اكتشاف ذاتك عن طريق فنك. أليس كذلك؟
And one thing about cars is we're all a little bit like Pygmalion,
و شيء واحد عن السيارات هو أن جميعنا بعض الشيء كالبيجماليون,
we are completely in love with our own creations.
و نحن مغرمون للغاية بابتكاراتنا.
This is one of my favorite paintings, it really describes our relationship with cars.
هذه إحدى لوحاتي المفضلة, إنها حقاً تصف علاقتنا بالسيارات.
This is sick beyond belief.
هذه مريضة إلى حد لا يصدق.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But because of this, the intimacy with which we work together as a team
و لكن بسبب هذا, الألفة بين الأشياء التي نعمل بها كفريق
takes on a new dimension, a new meaning.
تأخذ منحنى آخر, معنى جديد.
We have a shared center; we have a shared focus --
نحن لدينا نقطة التقاء مشتركة, و لدينا أيضاً تركيز مشترك,
that car stays at the middle of all our relationships.
أن السيارة يجب أن تبقى محور كل علاقاتنا.
And it's my job, in the competitive process, to narrow this down.
و مهمتى, في السياق التنافسي, هي أن أحدد هذا المفهوم.
I heard today about Joseph's death genes
سمعت اليوم عن جينات الموت لجوزيف
that have to go in and kill cell reproduction.
و التي يجب أن تدخل و تقتل تكاثر الخلايا.
You know, that's what I have to do sometimes.
أتعلمون, هذا هو ما يجب علي فعله في بعض الأحيان.
We start out with 10 cars; we narrow it down to five cars,
نحن نبدأ عادة بعشر سيارات, و من ثم يجب علينا أن نقلص هذا العدد إلى خمس سيارات,
down to three cars, down to two cars, down to one car,
إلى ثلاث سيارات, إلى سيارتان, إلى سيارة واحدة,
and I'm in the middle of that killing, basically.
و أنا في مركز هذا القتل, ببساطة.
Someone's love, someone's baby.
حب أحدهم, طفل أحدهم.
This is very difficult, and you have to have a bond with your team
إنها عملية صعبة للغاية, و يجب عليك أن يكون لديك رابط مع فريقك
that permits you to do this, because their life is wrapped up in that too.
بما يسمح لك أن تفعل ذلك, لأن حياتهم هي مرتبطة بهذا أيضاً.
They've got that gene infected in them as well,
هم مصابون بهذا الجين كذلك,
and they want that to live, more than anything else.
و هم يريدون لهذا الشيء أن يعيش, أكثر من أي شيء آخر.
Well, this project, Deep Blue, put me in contact with my team
حسناً, هذا المشروع, ديب بلو, وضعني على اتصال بفريقي
in a way that I never expected, and I want to pass it on to you,
بطريقة لم أعهدها من قبل, و أود أن أنقل تجربتي إليكم,
because I want you to reflect on this, perhaps in your own relationships.
لأنني أريد أن تطبقوا هذا الشيء, ربما في علاقاتكم الإجتماعية.
We wanted to a do a car which was a complete leap of faith for BMW.
أردنا أن نصنع سيارة تكون طفرة نوعية في مسيرة بي أم دبليو.
We wanted to do a team which was so removed from the way we'd done it,
أردنا أن نصنع فريقاً يكون مختلفاً كلياً عما كنا نفعله في السابق,
that I only had a phone number that connected me to them.
أنه كان لدي فقط رقم هاتف يربطني بهم.
So, what we did was: instead of having a staff of artists that are just your wrist,
أذاً, ما قمنا بفعله هو بدل أن يكون لدينا مجموعة من الفنانين يكونون رهن إشاراتك كما كان لدينا في السابق,
we decided to free up a team of creative designers and engineers
قررنا أن ننشئ فريقاً من المصممين و المهندسين الموهوبين
to find out what's the successor to the SUV phenomenon in America.
ليكتشفوا من تكون خليفة الـ اس يو في في أمريكا.
This is 1996 we did this project. And so we sent them off with this team name,
كان هذا عام 1996 عندما أنجزنا هذا المشروع. و هكذا أرسلناهم بهذا الإسم,
Deep Blue. Now many people know Deep Blue from IBM --
ديب بلو. هنالك العديد من الناس يعرفون ديب بلو من آي بي أم,
we actually stole it from them because we figured
في الواقع نحن قمنا بسرقته منهم لأننا تصورنا
if anybody read our faxes they'd think we're talking about computers.
إن قرأ أحدهم رسائلنا عبر الفاكس, فسيفكر على الفور بأننا نتكلم عن الحواسيب.
It turned out it was quite clever because Deep Blue,
و ظهر جلياً فيما بعد أن تسمية المشروع بـ ديب بلو كاننت خطوة موفقة,
in a company like BMW, has a hook -- "Deep Blue," wow, cool name.
في شركة كـ بي أم دبليو, لديها رنة -- ديب بلو, ياللهول, اسم مذهل.
So people get wrapped up in it. And we took a team of designers,
و كذلك إنضم الناس فيها. و جمعنا فريقاً من المصممين,
and we sent them off to America. And we gave them a budget,
و أرسلناهم الى أمريكا. و أعطيناهم ميزانية,
what we thought was a set of deliverables,
و قائمة بالأشياء التي يجب عليهم أن ينجزوها,
a timetable, and nothing else.
و جدول عمل, و لا شيء سوى ذلك.
Like I said, I just had a phone number that connected me to them.
و كما قلت سابقاً, لم يدكن لدي سوى رقم هاتف يصلني بهم.
And a group of engineers worked in Germany,
و مجموعة من المهندسين كانت تعمل في ألمانيا,
and the idea was they would work separately
و كانت الفكرة وقتئذٍ أن يعملوا منفصلين
on this problem of what's the successor to the SUV.
على إشكالية من يكون خليفة الـ إس يو في في أمريكا,
They would come together, compare notes. Then they would work apart,
و بعدها يجتمعون, يقارنون ملاحظاتهم. و بعدها يعملون منفصلين ثانية,
come together, and they would produce together
ثم يجتمعون, و عندها يمكنهم الإنتاج معاً
a monumental set of diverse opinions that didn't pollute each other's ideas --
لمجموعة كبيرة من الأفكار, لا تغض الطرف عن أفكار الطرف الآخر --
but at the same time came together and resolved the problems.
و لكن في نفس الوقت, تحل المشكلة.
Hopefully, really understand the customer at its heart,
و كان يؤمل, أن يتفهموا احتياجات الزبون,
where the customer is, live with them in America. So -- sent the team off,
حيثما كان يعيش, أن يعيشوا معه في أمريكا. إذاً -- أرسلنا الفريق,
and actually something different happened. They went other places.
و في الحقيقة حصل شيء آخر. لقد ذهبوا إلى أمكنة أخرى.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
They disappeared, quite honestly, and all I got was postcards.
لقد اختفوا, بصراحة, و كل ما حصلت عليه هو بطاقات بريد.
Now, I got some postcards of these guys in Las Vegas,
حصلت على بعض بطاقات البريد من أولئك الذين كانو في لاس فيغاس,
and I got some postcards of these guys in the Grand Canyon,
و حصلت كذلك على بطاقات بريد من أولئك الذين كانوا في غراند كانيون,
and I got these postcards of Niagara Falls,
و حصلت أيضاً على بطاقات بريد من شلالات نياغرا,
and pretty soon they're in New York, and I don't know where else.
و قريباً سيكونون في نيويورك, و لا أعلم أين أيضاً
And I'm telling myself, "This is going to be a great car,
و أنا أقول لنفسي, "ستكون هذه سيارة عظيمة,
they're doing research that I've never even thought about before."
إنهم يقومون بأبحاث لم أفكر بها سابقاً."
Right? And they decided that instead of, like, having a studio,
و قرروا أنه بدلاً من أن يكون لديهم ستوديو,
and six or seven apartments,
و ست أو سبع شقق,
it was cheaper to rent Elizabeth Taylor's ex-house in Malibu.
كان أرخص عليهم أن يستأجروا بيت إليزابيث تايلور القديم في ماليبو.
And -- at least they told me it was her house,
و -- على الأقل أخبروني أنه بيتها,
I guess it was at one time, she had a party there or something.
أظن أنه في وقت من الأوقات, كان لديها حفلة هناك أو شيء من هذا القبيل.
But anyway, this was the house, and they all lived there.
على كل حال, كان هذا هو البيت, و كلهم أقاموا هناك.
Now this is 24/7 living, half-a-dozen people who'd left their --
و الآن هذه حياتهم 24/7, نصف درزن من الأشخاص الذين تركوا ورائهم --
some had left their wives behind and families behind,
بعضهم قد تركوا أولادهم و عائلاتهم ورائهم,
and they literally lived in this house
و هم حقيقة عاشوا في هذا المنزل
for the entire six months the project was in America,
لمدة ستة أشهر كاملة,
but the first three months were the most intensive.
و لكن الشهور الثلاثة كانت هي الأكثر صعوبة.
And one of the young women in the project,
و أحدى الشابات في المشروع,
she was a fantastic lady, she actually built her room in the bathroom.
كانت شابة رائعة, لقد بنت غرفتها في الحمام.
The bathroom was so big, she built the bed over the bathtub --
كان الحمام كبيرا لدرجة أنها بنت سريرها فوق حوض الإستحمام --
it's quite fascinating.
إنه لشيء رائع حقاً.
On the other hand, I didn't know anything about this. OK?
في الجانب الآخر, لم أكن أعلم أي شيء عن هذا. حسناً؟
Nothing. This is all going on, and all I'm getting is postcards
لا شيء. كل هذا يجري, و كل ما كنت أحصل عليه هو البطاقات البريدية
of these guys in Las Vegas, or whatever,
من أولائك الأشخاص في لاس فيغاس, أو أياً كانوا,
saying, "Don't worry Chris, this is really going to be good." OK?
و يقولون لي, "لا تقلق يا كريس, سيكون هذا رائعاً حقاً." حسناً؟
So my concept of what a design studio was probably --
أذاً كان مفهومي لستوديو التصميم أنه كان غالباً --
I wasn't up to speed on where these guys were.
أني لم أكن على إطلاع كافي لما يقوم به أولئك الأشخاص.
However, the engineers back in Munich
لكن, المهندسون في ميونيخ
had taken on this kind of Newtonian solution,
كانو قد أخذوا في إيجاد حل نيوتوني نوعاً ما,
and they were trying to find how many cup holders
و كانوا يحاولون إيجاد عدد حاملات الأكواب
can dance on the head of a pin, and, you know,
التي يمكنها أن ترقص على رأس دبوس, و, تعلمون,
these really serious questions that are confronting the modern consumer.
هذه الأسئلة الجادة جداً التي كانت تواجه الزبون العصري.
And one was hoping that these two teams would get together,
و كان المرئ يأمل في أن يندمج هاتين الفريقين مع بعضهما البعض,
and this collusion of incredible creativity,
و هذا التلاحم للإبداع الرهيب,
under these incredible surroundings,
تحت هذه الظروف الرهيبة,
and these incredibly stressed-out engineers,
و أولئك المهندسون المتشددون لدرجة يصعب تخيلها,
would create some incredible solutions.
كان يمكن أن ينتج حلاً لا يصدق.
Well, what I didn't know was, and what we found out was --
حسناً, ما لم أكن أعرفه, و ما عرفناه لاحقاً هو أن --
these guys, they can't even like talk to each other under those conditions.
أولئك الشبان لم يكن باستطاعتهم التحدث مع بعضهم البعض تحت هذه الظروف.
You get a divergence of Newtonian and quantum thinking at that point,
كان هنالك اختلاف نيوتوني و كمي تفكيري في هذه النقطة,
you have a split in your dialog that is so deep, and so far,
لديك شق في حوارك و هو شق عميق و بعيد للغاية,
that they cannot bring this together at all.
و أنه لا يمكنهم جمع هذا الشق إطلاقاً.
And so we had our first meeting, after three months, in Tiburon,
و هكذا عقدنا أول اجتماع لنا, بعد ثلاثة أشهر, في تيبورن,
which is just up the road from here -- you know Tiburon?
و هي هنا على قارعة لطريق -- أتعرفون تيبورن؟
And the idea was after the first three months of this independent research
و كانت الفكرة أنه بعد ثلاثة أشهر من هذا البحث الذاتي
they would present it all to Dr. Goschel --
يجب عليهم تقديم النتائج كلها إلى دكتور غوشل --
who is now my boss, and at that time he was co-mentor on the project --
الذي بدوره أصبح رئيسي الآن, و كان وقتئذ مدير المشروع --
and they would present their results.
و كان عليهم تقديم النتائج.
We would see where we were going,
كنا نرى إلى أين نحن ذاهبون,
we would see the first indication of what could be
كنا نرى العلامات الأولى لما يمكنه أن يصبح
the successive phenomenon to the SUV in America.
الخليفة الناجحة للـ أس يو في في أمريكا.
And so I had these ideas in my head, that this is going to be great.
و هكذا كانت لدي تلك الأفكار في رأسي, أن هذا سيكون رائعاً.
I mean, I'm going to see so much work, it's so intense --
أعني, سوف أرى الكثير من الأعمال, إنه لشيء مثير حقاً --
I know probably Las Vegas meant a lot about it,
أعلم أن لاس فيغاس كانت ستكون لديها بعض اللمسات,
and I'm not really sure where the Grand Canyon came in either --
و لست متأكداً حقيقة أين سيأتي دور الـ غراند كانيون --
but somehow all this is going to come together,
و لكن بطريقة أو بأخرى كل هذا سيتكون مع بعضه البعض,
and I'm going to see some really great product.
و سوف أرى منتوجاً رائعاً حقاً.
So we went to Tiburon, after three months,
أذاً ذهبنا إلى تيبورن, بعد ثلاثة أشهر,
and the team had gotten together the week before,
و كان الفرق قد وصل إلى هناك قبل أسبوع,
many days ahead of time.
قبل الوقت المحدد بعدة أيام.
The engineers flew over, and designers got together with them,
طار المهندسون إلى المكان, و اجتمع معهم المصممون,
and they put their presentation together.
و قاموا بوضع عروضهم.
Well, it turns out that the engineers hadn't done anything.
حسناً, لقد تبين أن المهندسون لم يقوموا بأي شيء يذكر.
And they hadn't done anything because --
و لم يقوموا بأي شيء بسبب --
kind of, like in car business, engineers are there to solve problems,
نوعاً ما, في صناعة السيارات, المهندسون موجودون لحل المشاكل,
and we were asking them to create a problem.
و كنا قد طلبنا منهم أن ينشئوا المشكلة.
And the engineers were waiting for the designers to say,
و المهندسون كان ينتظرون المصمممين أن يقولوا لهم,
"This is the problem that we've created, now help us solve it."
"هذه هي المشكلة التي أنشأناها, الآن ساعدونا في إيجاد حل لها."
And they couldn't talk about it. So what happened was,
و لم يكن باستطاعتهم أن يتكلموا عنها. أذاً ما حصل هو التالي,
the engineers showed up with nothing.
ظهر المهندسون فارغي اليدين.
And the engineers told the designers,
و قد أخبر المهندسون المصممون,
"If you go in with all your stuff, we'll walk out,
"إن ذهبتم بكل ما عندكم, سوف ننسحب,
we'll walk right out of the project."
سوف ننسحب من المشروع."
So I didn't know any of this,
و لم أكن أعلم أي شيء عن هذا,
and we got a presentation that had an agenda, looked like this.
و قد كان لدينا عرض يحتوي على جدول أعمال, بهذا الشكل.
There was a whole lot of dialog.
كان هنالك الكثير من الحوارات.
We spent four hours being told all about vocabulary
لقد أمضينا أربع ساعات نستمع إلى شرح عن الكلمات
that needs to be built between engineers and designers.
التي يجب أن تبنى بين المهندسين و المصممين.
And here I'm expecting at any moment, "OK, they're going to turn the page,
و كنت أتوقع هنا في أي لحظة, "حسناً, سوف يطون الصفحة,
and I'm going to see the cars, I'm going to see the sketches,
سوف أرى سيارات, سوف أرى اسكتشات,
I'm going to see maybe some idea of where it's going."
سوف أرى ربما فكرة عما توصلوا إليه."
Dialog kept on going, with mental maps of words, and pretty soon
و لكن الحوارات استمرت, مع خرائط عقلية للكلمات, و عاجلاً
it was becoming obvious that instead of being dazzled with brilliance,
أصبحت العملية بدل أن تكون مليئة بالإبداع,
I was seriously being baffled with bullshit.
لقد أصابوني حقيقة بحيرة مليئة بالهراء.
And if you can imagine what this is like,
و إن كان بإمكانك أن تتصور المشهد,
to have these months of postcard indication of how great this team is working,
أن يكون لديك هذه الشهور المليئة بالبطاقات البريدية و التي تدل على أن الفرق كان يعمل عملاً رائعاً,
and they're out there spending all this money, and they're learning,
و هم هناك ينفقون كل هذه الأموال, و هم يتعلمون,
and they're doing all this stuff.
و هم يفعلون كل هذه الأشياء.
I went fucking ballistic, right? I went nuts.
لقد أصبت بالجنون. لقد طار عقلي.
You can probably remember Tiburon, it used to look like this.
يمكنكم أن تتذكروا تيبرون, لقد كانت تبدو كهذا.
After four hours of this, I stood up, and I took this team apart.
و بعد عدة ساعات من هذا, وقفت, و طلبت من هذا الفريق أن يتنحى جانياً
I screamed at them, I yelled at them, "What the hell are you doing?
و صرخت عليهم, "ما الذي تفعلونه؟
You're letting me down, you're my designers,
إنكم تخذلونني, أنتم مصمميي,
you're supposed to be the creative ones,
يجدر بكم أن تكونوا مبدعين,
what the hell is going on around here?"
ما الذي يحدث؟"
It was probably one of my better tirades, I have some good ones,
لقد كانت إحدى أفضل خطبي, لدي بعض الجيد منها,
but this was probably one of my better ones. And I went into these people;
و لكن كانت هذه أحدى أفضلهم. و توجهت نحو أولئك الأشخاص:
how could they take BMW's money,
كيف يمكنهم أن يأخذوا أموال بي أم دبليو,
how could they have a holiday for three months and produce nothing, nothing?
كيف يمكنهم أن يمضوا إجازة لمدة ثلاث أشهر, و ينتجوا لا شيء, لا شيء؟
Because of course they didn't tell us that they had three station wagons
لأنهم بالطبع لم يخبروني أنه لديهم ثلاث شاحنات
full of drawings, model concepts, pictures -- everything I wanted,
مليئة بالرسومات, المجسمات, صور -- و كل شيء أردته,
they'd locked up in the cars, because they had shown solidarity with the engineers --
كان كل هذا في السيارات, لأنهم كانوا قد تضامنوا مع المهندسين --
and they'd decided not to show me anything,
و قد قرروا أن لا يعرضوا لي شيئاً,
in order to give the chance for problem solving a chance to start,
لكي يمنحوا الفرصة للبدء بحل المشاكل,
because they hadn't realized, of course,
لأنهم لم يدركوا, بالطبع,
that they couldn't do problem creating.
أنه لا يمكنهم أن يصنعوا المشاكل.
So we went to lunch --
إذاً ذهبنا للغداء --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I've got to tell you, this was one seriously quiet lunch.
و علي أخباركم, لقد كان هذا غداءاً صامتاً للغاية.
The engineers all sat at one end of the table,
المهندسون جلسوا هادئين على طرف من الطاولة,
the designers and I sat at the other end of the table, really quiet.
و أنا و المصممين جلسنا على الطرف الآخر, بصمت شديد.
And I was just fucking furious, furious. OK?
و كنت غاضباً حقاً. حسناً؟
Probably because they had all the fun and I didn't, you know.
غالباً لأنهم استمتعوا بوقتهم و أنا لم تسنح لي فرصة ذلك, أتعلمون.
That's what you get furious about right?
هذا ما يغضبك عادة أليس كذلك؟
And somebody asked me about Catherine, my wife, you know,
و سألني أحدهم عن حال كاثرين, زوجتي,
did she fly out with me or something?
هل طارت معك أو شيء من هذا القبيل؟
I said, "No," and it triggered a set of thoughts about my wife.
و أجبت "لا," و قد أوقد عدة أفكار حول زوجتي.
And I recalled that when Catherine and I were married,
و تذكرت حينما تزوجنا أنا و كاثرين,
the priest gave a very nice sermon, and he said something very important.
و قد خطب يومها القسيس خطبة جميلة للغاية, و قال حينها شيء مهم للغاية.
He said, "Love is not selfish," he said,
قال, "الحب ليس أناني," قال,
"Love does not mean counting how many times I say, 'I love you.'
"الحب لا يعني أن تحصي كم مرة قلت, "أحبك."
It doesn't mean you had sex this many times this month,
إنه لا يعني كم مرة مارست الجنس في هذا الشهر,
and it's two times less than last month,
و إنها أقل بمرتين عن الشهر الفائت,
so that means you don't love me as much.
إذاً يعني هذا أنك لم تعد تحبني بالقدر ذاته.
Love is not selfish." And I thought about this, and I thought,
الحب ليس أنانياً." و فكرت في هذا, و فكرت,
"You know, I'm not showing love here. I'm seriously not showing love.
"أتدرون, أنا لا أظهر الحب هنا. أنا حقاً لا أظهر الحب هنا.
I'm in the air, I'm in the air without trust.
أنا في الهواء, أنا في الهواء بدون ثقة.
This cannot be. This cannot be that I'm expecting a certain number of sketches,
لا يجوز لهذا أن يحدث. لا يجوز أن أتوقع كمية من الرسمات,
and to me that's my quantification method for qualifying a team.
و بالنسبة لي هذه هي الطريقة لتقييم فريقي.
This cannot be."
هذا لا يجوز."
So I told them this story. I said, "Guys, I'm thinking about something here,
لذا أخبرتهم هذه القصة. قلت لهم, "أيها الرفاق, أنا أفكر بشيء الآن,
this isn't right. I can't have a relationship with you guys
هذا لا يجوز, لا يمكنني أن أكون على علاقة معكم
based on a premise that is a quantifiable one.
مبنية على مقدمة قابلة للقياس الكمي.
Based on a dictate premise that says, 'I'm a boss, you do what I say, without trust.'"
مبنية على مقدمة تقول, "أنا الرئيس, أنتم تفعلون ما آمركم به, بدون ثقة."
I said "This can't be."
قلت "هذا لا يصح."
Actually, we all broke down into tears, to be quite honest about it,
في الواقع, كلنا انفجرنا من البكاء, لكي أكون صريحاً معكم,
because they still could not tell me how much frustration they had built up
لأنه لم يكن بمقدورهم بعد, أن يخبروني مدى الإحباط الذي كان عليهم التعامل معه
inside of them, not being able to show me what I wanted,
بداخلهم, لعدم قدرتهم على أن يروني ما أردت رؤيته,
and merely having to ask me to trust them that it would come.
و أن يطلبوا مني أن أثق بهم أنها ستأتي.
And I think we felt much closer that day,
و أعتقد أننا شعرنا بالقرب من بعضنا أكثر في ذلك اليوم,
we cut a lot of strings that didn't need to be there,
و قد قطعنا الكثير من القيود التي ما كان يجب أن تكون هناك بالدرجة الأولى,
and we forged the concept for what real team and creativity is all about.
و غيرنا مفهوم الفريق الحقيقي و الإبداع كلياً.
We put the car back at the center of our thoughts, and we put love,
لقد وضعنا السيارة في قلب فكرنا, و وضعنا الحب,
I think, truly back into the center of the process.
أعتقد, حقاً, مرة أخرى في مركز العملية كلها.
By the way, that team went on to create six different concepts
بالمناسبة, ذاك الفريق صنع ستة مفاهيم أخرى
for the next model of what would be the proposal
للنموذج الذي بدوره سيكون الاقتراح
for the next generation after SUVs in America.
للجيل القادم بعد الـ أس يو في في أمريكا.
One of those was the idea of a crossover coupes --
واحدة من هؤلاء كانت فكرة الكوبيه --
you see it downstairs, the X Coupe -- they had a lot of fun with that.
ترونها في الأسفل, الـ أكس كوبيه -- لقد مرحوا كثيراً معها.
It was the rendition of our motorcycle,
لقد كانت التسليم لدراجتنا النارية,
the GS, as Carl Magnusson says, "brute-iful,"
الـ جي أس, كما يطلق عليها كارل ماجنوسون, "بروت-ايفل,"
as the idea of what could be a motorcycle, if you add two more wheels.
كما فكرة الدراجة النارية, إن أضفت إليها عجلتين.
And so, in conclusion, my lesson that I wanted to pass on to you,
و هكذا, كاستنتاج, درسي الذي أود أن أنقله لكم,
was this one here. I'm also going to steal a little quote out of "Little Prince."
كان هذا هاهنا. و أنا سأقوم بسرقة حكمة صغيرة من "الأمير الصغير."
There's a lot to be said about trust and love,
هنالك الكثير الذي يمكن أن يقال عن الثقة و الحب,
if you know that those two words are synonymous for design.
إن علمت أن تلك الكلمتين مرادفتين للتصميم.
I had a very, very meaningful relationship with my team that day,
لقد مررت, بعلاقة مجدية للغاية مع فريقي في ذلك اليوم,
and it's stayed that way ever since.
و لقد بقيت على هذا الوضع للأبد.
And I hope that you too find that there's more to design,
و أتمنى أنكم أنتم أيضاً تكتشفون أن هنالك المزيد من الأشياء في التصميم,
and more towards the art of the design, than doing it yourself.
و المزيد من الأشياء نحو فن التصميم, من مجرد القيام به بنفسك.
It's true that the trust and the love, that makes it worthwhile.
إنه لصحيح أن الثقة و الحب, هما اللذان يجعلانه جديراً بالإهتمام.
Thanks so much.
شكراً جزيلاً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)